<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Scots treacherous designes discovered, or, A result to the pamphlet, intituled, The Scots remonstrance with a true relation of their proceedings at Newcastle, Hereford, Newark, and other parts of this kingdome : wherein their hypocrisie in religion, ingratitude to the king, falsenesse to this kingdome, unmercifulnesse in plundring, crueltie in shedding of blood, causelesse boasting of valour, is layd open to the view of the world: as also, the true cause of their refusing piscopacy, and, adhering to the Covenant ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58779</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12395247</idno>
  <idno type="VID">61127</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240973756</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17643</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12395247</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61127)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 822:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Scots treacherous designes discovered, or, A result to the pamphlet, intituled, The Scots remonstrance with a true relation of their proceedings at Newcastle, Hereford, Newark, and other parts of this kingdome : wherein their hypocrisie in religion, ingratitude to the king, falsenesse to this kingdome, unmercifulnesse in plundring, crueltie in shedding of blood, causelesse boasting of valour, is layd open to the view of the world: as also, the true cause of their refusing piscopacy, and, adhering to the Covenant ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R.B. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Scots remonstrance.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Pamphlets.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61127:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61127:1"/>
            <p>THE Scots Treacherous Designes Discovered: <hi>OR,</hi> A Result to the Pamphlet, intituled, <hi>The Scots Remonstrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With a true Relation of their proceedings at <hi>Newcastle, Hereford, Newark,</hi> and other parts of this KINGDOME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein, Their</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Hypocrisie in Religion,</item>
                  <item>Ingratitude to the King,</item>
                  <item>Falsenesse to this Kingdome,</item>
                  <item>Unmercifulnesse in Plundring,</item>
                  <item>Crueltie in shedding of Blood,</item>
                  <item>Causelesse boasting of Valour, is layd open to the view of the world.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As also, The true cause of their</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>Refusing Episcopacy,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>And,</hi> Adhering to the Covenant.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Deare Brethren</hi> have
<q>
                  <l>Mel in ore, Verba lactis;</l>
                  <l>Fel in corde, Fraus in factis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>R.B.</hi> &amp; are to be sold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:61127:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61127:2"/>
            <head>THE Scots Treacherous Designes Discovered, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat now my fine Apologizing <hi>Jockie?</hi> What? vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating actions which might exceed the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-plot, and blush not? I had thought <hi>Bothell</hi> had not left brasse enough in <hi>Scotland</hi> uncoin'd, to have built a face to that Impudence, but what <hi>Wallace,</hi> a Wight, or other hardy Champion, have yee acoutred forth for this enterprize? certainly his next piece of justified Impudence will be the severall Murders of your Native Kings, together with <hi>Gouries</hi> most obedient Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towards King <hi>James.</hi> Sure this fine Rhetoricall Apology pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from some of <hi>Lowdens</hi> Spaniels, which with long attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his Lordship, have lickt so much Sence from his eloquent Spittle, that they now venture to write Apologies; as for his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, I beleeve he is very chary of writing for fear his hand should be guiltie of betraying his heart; but for the care of his tongue, I believe he is so much a Christian, that he believes the Lord hates a Double one; wherefore to prevent the malediction, he commonly makes use of three, one for the King, another for the Parliament, but the third for himselfe and fellow Confederates; yet all these mysti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally composed in one, and that closeted within the meager chops of a deceitfull <hi>Scot.</hi> But fearing lest I should be too bold with his honour, I shall returne to my businesse, which is to unravell the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent bottome of this confident vindicator.</p>
            <p>And first, my fine reformed Apologist makes it his businesse to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61127:3"/> excuse his Countreymen for their Rising in Rebellious Tumults, and in Armes against the King; and then he refines and minces the name of a Rebellions Insurrection into the fine modest name of a Convening of Nobilitie and Gentry, And they, not as Souldiers in a military posture, but as humble Suppliants with a Petition to his Majestie, to have the Grievances of their Country redressed. It was a very prettie new-found way (which hath beene oft used in <hi>England</hi> since) of petitioning, to bring a Petition in their pockets and Muskets on their shoulders; yet these Babes of Grace did not appeare as Enemies or Disturbers of the Peace of the Kingdome, but to settle a safe and wel-grounded Peace here, where there had beene no Warres since their remembrance.</p>
            <p>But it was Bishops that so troubled their peacefull Consciences, they favoured so of the Reliques of <hi>Rome;</hi> yea, the Figure of the Whore of <hi>Babylon;</hi> for they with their paintings and false dresses, which they put upon the word, tempted silly soules into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivitie; yea, they inforced the Spirit against its will; when now the blessed Covenant inforces nor compells none, but onely with a sweet sort of Gentle Imprisonment, and debarring them of their Liberties, and dispossessing them of their Estates by a Gentle way of Sequestration; but that is but the Blessed type of a hopefull Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and no Inforcement. But truely, all these conven'd Saints had very good reason to be inveterate against Bishops, all severally in their particular callings. As for the Nobilitie, their cause was evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and they ought to hate them were it but for this reason, That because the Bishops were indowed with more meanes, and assum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to themselves greater Estates by their Learning and Vertues, then many of the Nobilitie could purchase with their Salt-pans, Coale-pits, and such like <hi>Scotch</hi> Merchandize, with all their Coal-miners, and their Vices to boot.</p>
            <p>As for the Pulpit-knocking Clergie, they must needs hate them; for before the Bishops began to Rule in <hi>Scotland,</hi> there was a tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of Non-sence throughout the Kingdom. When now it was not stamping, knocking, and pronouncing dreadfull damnation, that procured Mas. <hi>John</hi> A Benefice; but now before hee can be trusted with a Parsonage, he must be capable of Speaking mildsense for feare of committing violence on the Cushion; and this was sufficient to cause the Clergy to convene. Then for the plaine down-right Case-eating Blew-cap, judge you but his just cause of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61127:3"/> convening; for before Bishops came in, then was the Bug-breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Scotch-cloth all in fashion, from the Mightie Madam in the Matted-chamber, to Muckell <hi>Maggy</hi> on the Medden, and then could <hi>Sandies</hi> wife and his three Bearnes caddle their eighteen-pence a weeke at Spinning, but now since the Prelates brought in Idolatrous Lawne first on his sleeves, now it is growne so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, that every Gill-flirt must have a Gorget on't, and hold the wholesome and comely Scotch-cloth in disdaine. This reason I suppose sufficient for blew-breeked <hi>Jockie</hi> to convene.</p>
            <p>But although these severall parties had so great a necessitie of convening, yet they did it not in a hostile way, for they sent not fire before them (nor altogether destruction behind them) but came in mildly with a Petition, onely indeed they were armed with Pike and Musket, Drum and Colours, but neither were their Pikes hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with fire as they might have beene, but with harmelesse Iron and Steele, and their Muskets onely loaden with compassionate Powder and mercifull Lead, and their Matches lighted but at one end, which shewed them to be no violent Enemies, but our loving Brethren and Friends, as their future actions have manifested.</p>
            <p>And then the just Christians (if they may allow'd that name) presume to boast how exact they have beene in giving an accompt for his Majesties Revenues in <hi>Scotland,</hi> they may well say an accompt, for his Majestie scarce ever received any thing out of the Kingdome but <hi>In primis</hi> and <hi>Items</hi> for all his Revenues there, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when he was last in <hi>Scotland,</hi> they were at the charges of swee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Holy-Rood</hi> house at <hi>Edenburg,</hi> and new scouring the Organs in the private Cappell; but no sooner was his Majesties back turn'd towards <hi>Scotland,</hi> and he marched into <hi>England,</hi> but they most de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutely converted the Organs into most reverend and melodious, Bag-pipes and tin Spoones. Yet some of the Nobilitie were so pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall to invite his Majestie, for whose Entertainment they most voluntarily did slay an Oxe and halfe a dozen Milch-Goates, with an old Tup Ram which served for Venison; but for this rioting, flesh was excommunicated their Kitchins for one quarter of a yeare, and the poore hungry Serving-men lived a moneth after on the steame of the Kitchin, and lickings of the Dripping-pans, and the reversions of mouldy crusts in the Pantry, and thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves in a continuall feast too; but in this supposed plentie they remained, till they looked like so many of <hi>Pharoah's</hi> leane Kine;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61127:4"/> but they did not onely prognosticate a future famine, but manifest a present, which made that provident <hi>Joseph,</hi> the good Lord <hi>Argile,</hi> to Assemble his Camells, and <hi>Lesley</hi> his Asses, to fetch in Provisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from the Neighbouring Countries; but <hi>England</hi> can testifie, that it was not Provisions alone that have satisfied these beasts since they first conven'd.</p>
            <p>Then you confesse, his Majesties Indulgent Clemency you cannot deny: In troth I wonder at it, ye being all so naturally of that trade that knowes the danger of confessing. Then you say, you went home so contentedly, hoping to live at peace and rest at home (how long thinke you yee might have staid there before yee had beene troubled by any? Sure till the last Trump blew; and 'tis a question whether yee will be taken notice on then or no: As for Heaven, ye are not so impudent to hope for it, and Hell will hardly be troub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with yee.)</p>
            <p>But how long pray did your contented life last at home? Why, till you had spent all the monies you had of your beloved Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> for so faithfully preferring your so well Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Petition, and that being once gone, the Bishops troubled you againe, and their Ecclesiasticall Government began to be very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fensive, and the Proctors and Registers would not accept of the Humiliation of <hi>Jockie</hi> of the Bray, and <hi>Jannet</hi> of the Dale, in the Solemne stoole of Repentance, but gude feith they must pay their Siller too; which tyranny over the cod-piece and placket was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knowne before in faire <hi>Scotland;</hi> wherefore I thinke it was no more then time to convene, to extirpate these Romish Prelates. But certainly <hi>Jockie</hi> it was not thy zeale to the Kirk, nor absolutely thy envy to the Bishops, that did first induce thee to convene; but thou sawest that good King <hi>Jeamy</hi> was dead, and that his Bearne was not so easily perswaded to give what thou hadst the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to aske; besides, you perceived that your double hearts and <hi>Janus</hi> faces were discovered in <hi>England,</hi> and how the most of you were baffel'd, hated, and scorn'd out of all company (which you did sufficiently merit) wherefore being conscious, you retired your selves home to your smokey Mansions, where with your ingendring with your Long-eared Priests, and mixing of Treason and Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my together, you at length with much adoe brought forth and spawn'd that wholesome Monster the Covenant, whose <hi>Hydra's</hi> head did so increase by reason of the mystery of the sence of it,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61127:4"/> the extirpating the Prelate being the pretended intention, and all assembled knowing no other intent, which being once conven'd, and in another petitionary and peacefull posture onely Armed for defence, and offence, you then not onely questioned the Prelates tyranny, as you called it, but began to limit the Kings Prerogative too, under the modest and carefull names of just Rights and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which are as your usage hath manifested, a confining of his Majestie to one punctuall place of being; and his Priviledges to play at Goffe or Bowles when you please to give him leave. A ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prettie sweet just Right and Prerogative for a Prince, and a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry solemne piece to ingage a Nation to a Sacramentall Oath to maintaine their Prince in such a Prerogative.</p>
            <p>Then after your second Qualification, O how jealous you were in raysing an Army for <hi>Ireland</hi> at your owne charges (as you call it) but it then cost the King treble the value onely towards it, (besides the accompts of his Revenues) and what service they have done there God knowes it, but no man can hardly testifie any thing of it, onely that the poore English Gentry and others that had any Estates left free from the Rebells, they wearied out of the Kingdom &amp; Country with their heavy oppressions that they might possesse themselves of their Estates, which they have done now.</p>
            <p>Indeed they twice besieged <hi>Charlemont,</hi> and to say truth, they were but twice beat from it; and at <hi>Black-water</hi> last yeare they had a glorious Victory, for the Lord was before them, Nay, all the Lords and Commanders they had were before them, but the <hi>Irish</hi> was in the Reare for ten miles, with the Devill to boot.</p>
            <p>And there you complaine that your men wanted Breeches and Shoes. Why? It is not unknowne to the world, that most of your Nation, till they came into <hi>England,</hi> did scarce thinke there were any such things Incident to nature; for yee are not onely borne without Breeches and Shoes, but bred without them, and being not used to them in your Infancy, I wonder how you have the Impudence to complaine for want of them in your age?</p>
            <p>Then thirdly, to shew your gratitude to his Majestie, and to set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle him in his throne, you convened againe, for the good of the King onely now, the Bishops being all suppressed, which evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared by your opposing of the Armies raised by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Command; but alas you could doe no more then you could doe, for it was against your Covenant to joyne with such wicked
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61127:5"/> persons as served the King, (besides the King had no hundred thousand pounds for you) and His Souldiers wronged the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try in taking meate for themselves of the Country, but you happy Israelites certainly lived on Celestiall Quailes and Manna, but most commonly ye found the Quailes in the Dove-Coats and Hen-Roomes, and the Manna in your Landlords Pantries, and Ambries. And as for plundering houses, you scorned it, (but what was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary for you) but you with a religious Sacrilege fell upon Churches, not plundering them, but modestly reforming the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices into Sarkes and reverent Nightcaps, the Common-Prayer Booke into Tobacco Papers, and the Consecrated Chalice blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reformed into a Candle-Cup for Mas. <hi>Iohn</hi> your prick-card Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, which he after a long Grace, devoutly drinkes some sixe times full to strengthen him in a long-winded exercise; and such hopefull Babes could no waies joyne with the Kings party without hazard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the breach of your Cordiall Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to your boasting:</hi> First for your battle at <hi>Marston More,</hi> I am confident your Generall cannot give an account of any thing done that day after the warning Peece was shot: for his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy was thirty miles from the place before the fight was done, a shifting a shirt, and bewailing the death of his deare Countrimen; And after at <hi>New-Castle</hi> where you were so mercifull, the Towne cannot but witnesse your civility in plundering, when you left not an Ale-wife a Spicket and Fosset to set up trading againe with, and there was not Canvas enough left in Towne to make a Hauking bagge, and yet the harmelesse Creatures did not plunder neither. And I beleeve the Countries can witnesse how civill you were in your march towards <hi>Hereford,</hi> when the people wrung their Bells for joy of your comming, but at your departure they wrung their hands; and I doubt not out to make up the Peale to see you wrung by the e ares for your civility: for in that march Beefe and Mutton was too grosse meat for your queasie stomachs, which were bred up with junkets of long Cale, and refined Oatemeale; and when they wanted shooes, (which they complaine of) they made bold with their Landlords Bootes, vestures that neither they, nor their Fore-fathers were guilty of wearing. But how thinke yee they came by these habiliments? why? first in their march they made Malignants, then search'd their houses for Armes, and finding such dangerous Instruments of War, as Bootes, Breeches, Coates and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61127:5"/> Shirts, and other such offensive weapons, as by your Covenant you were bound, seized on them, this being the onely way for the setling of a well grounded Peace in both Kingdomes, and it much conducing to the Liberty of the Subject.</p>
            <p>Then for your not thirsting after bloud, let <hi>Canfrome</hi> bee witnesse; where yee spared not the life of either man or woman, but only two old wives, who had long time beene suspected to be of the same trade that most of your mothers were of; Then when you were before <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reford,</hi> you were indeed so carefull of the quiet of the Countrey, that ye scarce left an Oxe or Sheepe within ten miles to disturbe it, or a Cock to crow, or Goose to hisse at ye, for feare of disturbing the rest and Peace of the Kingdome. Then in your march back again, I think you shewed your selves the same men that marched that waies before; for ye used the same civility.</p>
            <p>But now my friends, for your fine usage of His Majesty a word or two, sure you cannot be so impudent, to deny but with many private Letters, and crafty Sollicitours, you were continually inviting His Majesty down to your Army, and how you used Him there I can something testifie. First you debarred admittance of any to His Majestie if he spoake any Language but the Language of the heathen your Country-men: you were so curteously obedient that you would peruse His Letters from His Queene, fearing lest there might be some French plots in them against the safety of His Majesties Person.</p>
            <p>A Court was kept for Him, but <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> had as civill homage done to him in the Forrest, when he was metamorphosed, by the beasts, as you bestowed on your King at <hi>New-Castle,</hi> and his fare was of far more delicacy: yet you allowed Him meate I confesse, and it was so be cooked, that if ever the Litanie come up againe, we will have it fixed with an Imprecation to be delivered from them.</p>
            <p>A Guard he had, but no devourers of Bull-beefe, for since their first essence they never tasted any flesh beyond Tripes and Livers; instead of the honourable badges of <hi>Yorke</hi> and <hi>Lancaster</hi> upon their backe and breasts, they wore the lively achievements of <hi>Aberdene</hi> and <hi>Dundee,</hi> with more Legions of puissant Lice traversing over their Scab-bemoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind bodies: But then to shew His Majestie the true worship of God, and the Reformed Kirk in her Glorie, O what plenty of <hi>Ionahs</hi> did the monstrous Fish, the Kirke of <hi>Scotland,</hi> vomit forth to Prophecie the destruction of great <hi>Ninivy,</hi> with the King thereof! they were da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Priests, what Pulpit Treason did they venter on? the which with his desperate knocking on the Court-Cubbord, which kept time with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61127:6"/> his blasphemy till the whole Auditory were weary of him, all his matter being the holy Covenant; first he declares, no Covenant no Salvation, no Covenant no Peace, nay, if the King tooke it not, there could be no Government for Him nor His Kingdom, but He and His Posterity must absolutely perish; more, if He tooke not the solemne Covenant, He could never make restitution for the bloud shed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which the Lord would require at His hands at the last day; this was not preached in a private Chappell, but openly in the Royall Presence of the King: And certainly these were seducing Motives to tempt the King to Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heare to their Reformation.</p>
            <p>Nobility they had some which served for Court Ciphers, still watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when the King would invest them with new honours, but His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty thinking none merited so well as <hi>Lastly</hi> first dubd him with a Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shion, and next wit a Trencher.</p>
            <p>The first, because out of the affection he had to His Majesty, and His Friends he proclaymed it death for any that had served in his Majesties War to stay in <hi>New-Castle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second, for the care he had of His Majestie by setting a double Guard at His Bed-chamber doore in <hi>New-Castle,</hi> a courteous gratitude to His Majesty for all honour imposed upon him. Nay, <hi>Scotch</hi> Leards were at the charge of putting themselves in Bootes and Hats, which thing neither they nor their Predecessors ever knew since the time of <hi>Iudas Escariot,</hi> who was the Patriarke of the Nation, And these panch-bellyed Disloyallists being big with Ambition made a journey to Court on purpose to produce a small Knighthood, which proved null; for there they stood labouring for honour (which the titurary Court Lords had promised them) taking as much paines for it, as <hi>Dametas</hi> did for the Treasure under the Stone, and to as much purpose; but for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee that sate there, the <hi>Contrivers of the French Massacre,</hi> nor <hi>Catesby</hi> and his confederates in the Powder Plot, were not halfe so perfidious, nor their consultations so destructive, this looked like <hi>Herods</hi> judgement Hall in the Hangings, where <hi>Louderdalle</hi> &amp; <hi>Argile</hi> looked like the two false witnesses, whilst <hi>Lowden</hi> sate like <hi>Pontius Pylate,</hi> but with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>washed hands.</p>
            <p>And these are they that my pretty vindicator endeavours to justifie for selling their King; but alas, they did not sell Him, they did (as the Welch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man did with his Hare) if the Parliament would lend them two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thousand pounds, then they would lend them the King, not sell Him by any meanes; but they thought themselves not able to protect His Person from danger, therefore it was convenient He should go to a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61127:6"/> place of more safetie, and no sooner they had their two hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pound, but they obediently told his Majestie that he must goe to his Parliament, and so left him to the conduct of I know not whom, neither did they care: But they deserved the summe of Money had the King never come to them, having had but three hundred thousand pound for the raysing and maintaining an Army of thirtie thousand men for three yeares.</p>
            <p>Thirtie thousand men <hi>Jockie?</hi> A goodly Army, but how many of the first twentie foure thousand ranne away and durst not see the Enemy? Above ten thousand; and the last six thousand never were above foure, whereof two of them came out of <hi>Ireland;</hi> but grant you had thirtie thousand men and but this three hundred thousand pound, I hope you would be pleased to remember other triviall summes that came in by the by; as two hundred &amp; fiftie thousand pound for Coales at <hi>Newcastle,</hi> and fifty thousand pound at <hi>Hereford,</hi> beside some such small summe at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke.</hi> And then free quarter was nothing; for you being bred always with Grasse, lived here upon Hay and such Rubbish, as Turkies, Capons, and Chickens, and such ordinary meat, which thousands of your Leards at home will goe fortie miles to behold and admire, and be satisfied with the sight, for tasting was beyond their hopes; then you had a pretty trick called Trencher-Mony too, the which was, 6. pence for every Landlord to pay to each Soldier, that they would be favourably pleased to undoe him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Courteously then to your kindnesse,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Too many neglected Gentlemen which had beene of the Kings Party, which thought to have sheltred themselves under you in their distresse, when the King desired you to relieve them and you engaged your selves to him that you would, yet all the reliefe you did administer, was a groat a day to Gentlemen that had kept your betters to their Groomes, and this groat was exacted from the poore Countrey too, which were doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly over-burdened by you before, by your heavy Taxes and Contributi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; so that ye may well bring in the North Country to be witnesses of your Civill behaviours, when you forced your poore Landlords to sell their Coats from their backs to buy sawce for their own Powltry; &amp; for Beefe and Muttons, what yee eate not, yee sent away and carried it to <hi>Scotland,</hi> for they were all Malignants on the other side <hi>Trent;</hi> but cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly yee are much wronged and abused by many, that avouch that you will not eate Swines flesh, when the Countrey can testifie you left not Swine enough in the Countrey to evacuate enough excrement to serve your Landresses to cleanse your Linnen (that being the onely Soape they use) no there was hardly a Hogge in the Countrey but those that were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61127:7"/> Commanders in the Army; then another very prettie trick you had, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Lift Money, which was at your departure, to inforce the Countrey to advance you ten dayes pay for your march home, besides the loane of their Horses (the which they might safely have taken a solemne leave off) to carry the goods with which you (I will not say did Plunder) but had use for in <hi>England;</hi> but I must be so uncivill to say, that verily you did as it were Plunder in <hi>Carlile;</hi> for where many families had left the Towne because their houses were infected, you being fill'd with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, according to the measure of grace the Devill had left you, most faire and honestly opened the windowes of the said houses, and in your care brought forth the goods, carrying them to <hi>Scotland</hi> to be aired and cleansed, where God was so just to punish you with the disease you Plundred from <hi>Carlile;</hi> and this is part of the faire and civill carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages that my fine Apologist undertakes to vindicate; had his cause beene mine I should soone have relinquished it with shame, but in discovering his fathers and brethrens nakednesse, he doth perfectly demonstrate his and their Geneology to be derived from the loines of cursed <hi>Ham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then in your future intentions, how jealous you would faine seeme to be for the true worship of God, when it is not unknowne to the world, whom yee call for witnesse of your integritie, that you are the greatest hypocrites in it: And you know, that through all the world yee are branded with the name of false-hearted <hi>Scots;</hi> and surely you are a blessed sweet people, and very likely to make a happy Reformation; And certainly we ought to hazard our Lives and Estates for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishment of it. And then you protest, that if any shall intrench on his Majesties just Rights and Priviledges, to settle him in his throne again: Good <hi>Jockie,</hi> who were they that first troubled him in it? And how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Fast and Loose Tricks have you shew'd him since? And thinke you his Majestie will trust to you now? No surely, the King hath had tryall enough of your fidelitie already, and the Kingdome of your civilitie and kindnesse: From which, with your farther assistance, Good Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us.</p>
            <p>And Now I hope I have discovered the <hi>Scot</hi> according to my weake abilitie; but what is done is nothing but what is veritie and cleare from malice, but very neere to the true colours of their actions past: For those to come, I feare I must leave to be sensured by the judicious; and for this time, goe no farther then my owne knowledge.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>